(soft music)
- [Narrator] In the
southern part of Japan,
you can find something
strange on satellite images.
Here is the city of Nagasaki
and right nearby there are
a couple of small islands.
Some of them are empty,
some house beach resorts,
but then there's this island,
densely packed with destroyed
wounds of a former city.
Google Street View works here.
You can drop a pin, walk around,
and explore the empty streets
and abandoned buildings.
(dramatic music)
It looks eerie.
And it's plain to see that
this island has been abandoned
for quite some time,
but yet even with nothing
left but ruins here,
this tiny piece of land
has a big story to tell.
One that is much larger than
recent Japanese history.
It stands as a chronicle
of global conflict,
the rise and fall of an empire,
and this island is the cause of a conflict
that is still ongoing even today.
This is Hashima.
(soft music)
What drew me to this topic initially
is that in many ways the story
of this island directly mirrors the story
of Japan as a nation.
In the late 1800s,
Japan experienced an industrial revolution
that fundamentally
transformed the country .
Japan moved from being a
nation rooted in agriculture,
to become a major industrial power.
Railroads were constructed,
factories sprung up,
shipyards were established,
and all this change required energy,
which led to the establishment
of new mines across the country,
including on Hashima.
(dramatic music)
Coal was discovered down in the seabed
beneath this rugged island in the 1800s
and the rapidly growing
Mitsubishi Corporation
caught wind of this discovery
and bought the entire island
to mine the coal to use as fuel
for its expanding fleet of steamships.
And just as coal mining
on the island was booming,
coal production in all of
Japan was breaking records.
In 1874,
Japan extracted 208,000 tons of coal.
By 1890, this figure had
searched to 3 million tons,
and by 1919
it had reached
31 million tons.
(soft music)
As the mine continued to
grow into the early 1900s,
the need for more workers
and more space increased.
Therefore, Mitsubishi
started to expand the size
of the island using the slag
produced from the coal mine
to artificially widen the island.
In order to protect the
more fragile flat land
that was reclaimed,
a concrete wall was
constructed around the island
to protect it from the violent waves
and typhoons that would crash against it.
This new space would be mostly
used for mining facilities
with living space dedicated
to the rocky North on
original island soil.
(soft music)
And just like the island was expanding,
the Japanese empire as a whole
was also expanding its
territorial control.
Driven by the desire to secure
resources and influence,
Japan occupied part of the Sakhalin Island
as well as Korea,
imposing its rule on local populations.
Meanwhile, on Hashima,
space was used as effectively as possible.
Rather than dedicate any
precious land for farming,
food, and fresh water
were instead shipped in
from mainland Japan.
This way, every inch of the island
that wasn't used for mining,
could instead be used
to build more housing structures
and to build supporting
facilities for miners
and their families, such as
a school, hospital, shops,
and a movie theater.
They even built a Pachinko parlor,
which is a place where
workers can go and gamble.
(soft music)
As Hashima continued expanding,
adding more artificial land
and springing up more concrete structures,
it began to take on its
characteristic shape.
When viewed from land,
the island would appear
like a large gray ship,
and people began referring
to the island as Gunkanjima,
literally meaning Battleship Island.
And in the 1930s,
as the island increasingly
resembled a battleship,
more and more real warships
began to navigate the seas around it.
(dramatic music)
That is because during the same time,
Japan found itself embroiled
in several conflicts,
most significantly with
the Republic of China.
In 1931, Japan invaded Manchuria,
and in 1937, a full scale
invasion of China began,
sparking the Second Sino-Japanese War.
With Japan aiming to expand
its empire even further,
this conflict would later become part
of the larger Second World War.
(soft music)
The demand for coal
was at an all-time high
during this period,
and Hashima reached its
peak production in 1941,
churning out 410,000 tons
of coal in that year.
And Mitsubishi, the company
operating the Hashima mine,
was also producing the warships
that the coal was used for
as well as aircraft and
other weaponry for the war.
With an ever expanding island,
the ever expanding empire
gained massive control in Asia,
an expansion that came at a massive cost,
as Japan forcibly
territories across the region
imposing its rule and
exploiting resources,
a story to which we all know how it ends.
(loud explosions)
On August 6th, 1945,
Hiroshima was the target
of the first atomic bombing.
(loud explosion)
Three days later, a second
bomb would be dropped,
the target, the city of
Nagasaki, right near Hashima.
(soft music)
In the aftermath of the bomb,
it was workers from Hashima
that were ferried to the scene
to help clean up the rubble.
And once again, the island
of Hashima was deeply tied
to the events that would
shape Japanese history.
Just four days later, Japan surrendered.
Ironically, just as coal from
minds like Hashima was used
to fuel Japan's war efforts,
it would also help fuel
the nation's recovery
after Japan's defeat at
the end of World War II.
In a short time, Japan went from a rival,
to a strategic ally for the United States,
acting as an operating base
and source of cheap goods
leading into the Korean War in 1950.
(soft music)
All industries, including coal,
saw a huge economic rise during this time,
and Hashima, once more, began
to bring prosperity to Japan.
With this continued
rising demand for coal,
came the increasing demand
for even more workers,
and by 1959, Hashima reached
its height in population,
with 5,259 people crammed
into its extremely tight living quarters,
making it the most densely populated place
in Japanese history at the time.
And yet, coal is a limited resource.
By the 1970s, the mine on
Hashima began to tap out,
and at around the same time,
petroleum began replacing coal
as the defacto fuel source.
In response, Mitsubishi
announced in January of 1974
that it would be closing
the mine and all residents
and workers would need to
leave in just three months,
with the last boat taking away Hashima's
remaining inhabitants in April of 1974.
(dramatic music)
From then on, Hashima remained closed,
with entry forbidden for decades.
Mitsubishi still owned the land,
but had no incentive to
upkeep any of the structures,
and so they began to crumble and decay.
What was once a bustling community,
became a ghost town,
which itself began
to attract attention from frill seekers
and the dark tourism community.
Despite being off limits,
adventurers would find ways
to get to the island,
exploring the buildings
as they were falling apart.
(dramatic music)
But then, in 2009, the Japanese
government changed course
and decided to open the
island back up for tourists.
Officially sanctioned
tourist groups would be
allowed to step on the island.
For this purpose, a new docking area
and fortified walkways were installed
on the sovereign part of the island.
Here, tourist boats can dock
and be shown around the island,
and the island would yet again contribute
to the Japanese economy,
now as a place for tourism.
To coincide with the official
reopening of Hashima,
and perhaps to encourage more
visitors to this destination,
Japan put forward a request
to have Hashima inscribed
as a world heritage site,
a UNESCO title
that would bring legal
protection to the site
as a recognized landmark.
Everything seemed to be
in order for the proposal
and the request was submitted
to UNESCO for review,
but then, before anything
could be finalized,
an outpouring of resistance
came from South Korea,
North Korea, and China, who
all opposed the proposal.
But why would they care so much
about a tiny Japanese island
that was once used for coal mining?
The answer lies in the
true history of Hashima,
the version that Japan
has continually attempted
to deny and cover up,
because while the story we
told so far was correct,
it also was incomplete,
because in reality, Hashima
wasn't just a coal mine,
it was essentially a prison.
(soft music)
As Japan expanded its
empire throughout Asia,
it wasn't just a demand for
coal that had increased,
but also the demand for soldiers.
Japanese and Korean men were
drafted into the imperial army,
leaving a large gap in
the industrial workforces.
And to fill this gap,
man and boys from Korea were
forcibly conscribed to work,
including for companies like Mitsubishi.
And as Japan continued conquering China,
Chinese prisoners of war were also used
for forced labor at many
industrial postings,
including Hashima.
Conditions for these forced
laborers were extremely harsh.
And one of the survivors
of Hashima, Suh Jung-woo,
described what it was
like for those conscribed
Jung-woo was forced out
of his village when he
was only 14 years old,
as a boat took him closer to Hashima
and he saw the concrete sea wall meant
to protect the island.
To him, it looked more like a prison wall
meant to keep those
captured locked within.
He was put in one of the
small apartment units
with six or seven other forced laborers.
Working inside the mine was brutal,
with temperatures reaching
up to 37 degrees Celsius,
mixed with high humidity.
Space was extremely limited down below,
just as it was on the surface,
meaning workers had to crouch
and crawl for much of
their 12 hour shifts.
And accidents were very common.
As with limited safety standards,
rock slides threatened
to crush the workers every day.
And while Jung-Woo survived
his ordeal on Hashima,
many of the hundreds
of Korean and Chinese prisoners did not.
And it is this darker past of the island
that the Japanese government
is obscuring until today.
Many survivors claim
that those who perished
during their captivity on the island
were taken to the nearby
island, Nakanoshima.
Here, their remains would be cremated,
sending columns of black
smoke into the sky,
that could be seen from Hashima,
giving a bleak reminder of the fate
that could be awaiting those who remained,
though disinformation
is to this day disputed
as Japan has denied the existence
of a crematorium on
the neighboring island.
The application for a world
heritage site would take years,
and after lots of back and forth,
a breakthrough came in 2015,
after Japan struck a
deal with South Korea,
and part of the deal was
that Japan would display
information about the forced
labor history at Hashima Island
visible for all the tourists visiting.
With South Korea's support,
Hashima was officially designated
a UNESCO World Heritage
Site, but almost immediately,
the Japanese government
walked back the promise.
A controversial statement
was released that claimed
that the Korean and Chinese workers
were legally drafted for work
just as Japanese men were also drafted
for military service.
Only in 2023, after
facing severe backlash,
some small steps were taken
to provide additional context.
At the Industrial Heritage
Information Center in Japan,
a small exhibit on
Hashima includes a QR code
that can be scanned,
bringing up a video of the 2015
UNESCO committee discussion
where Japanese ambassador made a statement
regarding the acknowledgement
of forced labor at
locations such as Hashima.
However, the statements made
in the video are in English,
with no Japanese subtitles.
To this day, the question of how Hashima
will be remembered remains contentious.
Even though relations between South Korea
and Japan are stable
considering the bloody past,
locations like Hashima show
that not all wounds are completely healed.
(soft music)
To me, the island is a fascinating example
of how we think about the past.
When we talk about history,
it is often at a grand scale.
Maps of expanding
empires, shifts in power,
wars waged and won,
but that view can make us forget
how deeply history is woven
into the places we inhabit every day.
(dramatic music)
Hashima is a great reminder
that history isn't just a story
of nations and movements,
it's the story embedded
in every place we stand,
a reminder that the local and
the global, are not separate.
That they're intertwined,
each telling the story of the other.
(dramatic music)
(soft music)
This was a story I've been
meaning to tell for a while
and I'm glad that I finally
got to put it on YouTube,
but there are a couple of things
that are not ideal.
For videos to be able to
make ad money on YouTube,
they have to be advertiser friendly,
which is just not the case
with certain subject matters,
such as a video I made about
the crash of flight MH17,
a civilian airliner that was
shot down over Eastern Ukraine,
or my video about the Bin Laden rid,
detailing how the compound
of the Al-Qaeda leader was raided,
a fascinating story,
but a brutal subject matter
doomed to get demonetized.
It turns out a lot of
creators feel that way.
And so what we did is
we all joined together
to build a solution.
(dramatic music)
It's called Nebula,
and it's our very own streaming service
where you can watch all these
exclusive videos of mine.
And since Nebula is a
subscription service,
it allows us to create more ambitious,
higher budget productions.
Besides my own exclusive video series,
we also have creator run game shows,
incredible documentaries,
narrative short films,
and full length feature films,
all done by independent creators
and supported by a growing
number of subscribers.
Plus, we always post
our videos there early,
so you can already watch my
next video on Nebula today.
So go to Nebula.tv/neo
and make sure that you
use exactly this link
in order to get 40% of the annual plan.
All my exclusive videos are up there,
so thanks for the support
and thank you so much
for watching this video.
(dramatic music)